<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>@carnby</title><link href="http://carnby.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://carnby.github.io/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://carnby.github.io/</id><updated>2014-01-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Data Portraits</title><link href="http://carnby.github.io/data-portraits.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>egraells</name></author><id>tag:carnby.github.io,2014-01-01:data-portraits.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is the second key project of my doctoral thesis. It's a joint work with my co-advisor &lt;a href="http://www.dcs.gla.ac.uk/~mounia/"&gt;Mounia Lalmas&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://researchswinger.org/"&gt;Daniele Quercia&lt;/a&gt;. Likewise the Virtual Ornithology project, it's about user behavior in Twitter. In particular, we want to find out &lt;em&gt;how to connect people with opposing views in controversial and sensitive issues&lt;/em&gt; by using &lt;em&gt;playful information visualizations&lt;/em&gt; like this one:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/visualizations-2013-data-portraits.png" width="600" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two behavioral bias related to this research project: &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Homophily"&gt;homophily&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Selective_exposure_theory"&gt;selective exposure&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. Homophily refers to connecting and having relationships with people similar to us, while selective exposure is the act of preferring to read information that reafirms our beliefs, and discarding information that do not. Previous work has intented to solve this problem by, for instance, recommending people that is dissimilar (i.e., they have opposing views), or by displaying challenging information to user's beliefs. It hasn't worked because users do not value diversity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our hypothesis is that this problem can be solved if, in addition to algorithms that perform people and content recommendation, we focus on &lt;em&gt;how to display those algorithm outcomes&lt;/em&gt;. In particular, we propose that &lt;em&gt;playful information visualization techniques&lt;/em&gt; will allow us to avoid the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cognitive_dissonance"&gt;cognitive dissonance&lt;/a&gt; of confronting challenging information. As algorithm we consider a new algorithm that will recommend people that has opposing views in sensitive issues, but that is similar in non-sensitive issues (for instance, people who thinks differently on abortion but that likes the same movies).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a case study, we analyzed Twitter users from Chile in the context of the &lt;em&gt;abortion&lt;/em&gt; issue (recall that there are two prominent stances: &lt;em&gt;#prochoice&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;#prolife&lt;/em&gt;). First, we tested our idea that intermediary topics, those that are able to connect people with different viewpoints in abortion. It turns out that, indeed, they exist! We detected them by using &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Latent_Dirichlet_allocation"&gt;topic modelling&lt;/a&gt; techniques. We presented these results at the &lt;a href="http://scholar.google.es/citations?view_op=view_citation&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;user=ltsTTI4AAAAJ&amp;amp;citation_for_view=ltsTTI4AAAAJ:u9iWguZQMMsC"&gt;2014 International World Wide Web Conference held in Seoul&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have evaluated our visualization in a pilot study with promising results. Results are reported in this &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1311.4658"&gt;pre-print&lt;/a&gt; and covered by:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.technologyreview.com/view/522111/how-to-burst-the-filter-bubble-that-protects-us-from-opposing-views/"&gt;MIT Technology Review&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://radar.oreilly.com/2013/12/four-short-links-3-december-2013.html"&gt;O'Reilly Radar&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://beta.slashdot.org/story/195089"&gt;slashdot&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.smithsonianmag.com/innovation/have-scientists-found-a-way-to-pop-the-filter-bubble-180948265/?no-ist"&gt;Smithsonian&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.wired.it/internet/regole/2013/12/13/come-usare-twitter-per-facilitare-il-confronto-tra-opposte-vedute-rete/"&gt;WIRED.it&lt;/a&gt; (in italian)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.ticbeat.com/socialmedia/somos-capaces-de-tolerar-opiniones-contrarias-la-nuestra-en-la-red-para-navidad/"&gt;TIC Beat Interview&lt;/a&gt; (in spanish)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently we are working on a more complete and longitudinal user study, with an improved visualization design. Stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="visualization"></category><category term="social network analysis"></category><category term="filter bubble"></category></entry><entry><title>Ficciones (in spanish)</title><link href="http://carnby.github.io/ficciones-in-spanish.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>egraells</name></author><id>tag:carnby.github.io,2014-01-01:ficciones-in-spanish.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://ficciones.cl"&gt;&lt;img src="images/ficciones.png" width="600" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ficciones&lt;/em&gt; is a blog where I publish short stories in spanish. The stories are about memory, literature, love and childhood. I actually stopped writing 8 years ago, until now... sometimes life hits you hard and deep. Maybe it hits harder if you are doing a PhD. Maybe not. &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="fiction"></category><category term="writing"></category><category term="memory"></category><category term="fantasy"></category></entry><entry><title>matta</title><link href="http://carnby.github.io/matta.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>egraells</name></author><id>tag:carnby.github.io,2014-01-01:matta.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;matta&lt;/code&gt; is my free (as in speech) library to be used within the IPython notebook. The idea is to have a bridge between typical data structures in Python (like networkx's graph and pandas DataFrames) to be visualized directly into the notebook using &lt;code&gt;d3.js&lt;/code&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see some basic examples in this &lt;a href="http://nbviewer.ipython.org/github/carnby/matta/blob/master/matta/notebooks/examples.ipynb"&gt;IPython notebook&lt;/a&gt;.
But you can also build cooler stuff like this map of Santiago (playing with the &lt;a href="http://transantiago.cl/dtpm/index.php/matrices-de-viaje"&gt;public transport system Transantiago Origin/Destiny matrix&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/visualizations-2014-matta-graph-map.png" width="600" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or this one (playing with Magic: The Gathering tournament results, an on-going project with &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/aastroza"&gt;Alonso Astroza&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/visualizations-2014-matta-mtg.png" width="600" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this using only code within the IPython notebook! You can see the code at &lt;a href="http://github.com/carnby/matta"&gt;github&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="IPython"></category><category term="d3.js"></category><category term="free software"></category></entry><entry><title>Virtual Ornithology</title><link href="http://carnby.github.io/virtual-ornithology.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>egraells</name></author><id>tag:carnby.github.io,2014-01-01:virtual-ornithology.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is one of the two key projects of my doctoral thesis (see its &lt;a href="http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2567958"&gt;proposal&lt;/a&gt;). It is about understanding how a virtual population behaves in Twitter in the presence of systematic biases that may affect its behavior. In particular, we focus in the population of Chile, and study how people behave in the context of &lt;em&gt;geographical centralization&lt;/em&gt;. Our main research question is: &lt;em&gt;how can we diminish the effect of centralization in the virtual population?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As dataset we consider a set of tweets crawled during the municipal elections in Chile held in 2012. Here is a wordcloud of the most frequent terms in the collection, after a cleaning process:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/visualizations-2014-virtual-ornithology.png" width="600" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We tested if the virtual population was representative of the physical population, and we found that it was spatially representative:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/visualizations-2014-population-distributions.png" width="600" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we did to test the existance of centralization was to build an &lt;em&gt;interaction graph&lt;/em&gt; where locations interact between them based on how people mention, reply and retweet people from other locations. This is a visualization of that interaction graph (on the left is the &lt;em&gt;source location&lt;/em&gt;; on the right, the &lt;em&gt;target location&lt;/em&gt; of the interaction graph):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/visualizations-2014-location-interactions.png" width="600" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though the population in Chile is imbalanced, the &lt;em&gt;observed&lt;/em&gt; amount of interactions to &lt;em&gt;Santiago/Región Metropolitana&lt;/em&gt; is higher than expected. To analyze this, we developed a methodology to define how centralized the virtual population is, and then we defined an algorithm to actually improve the situation. You can read more about it in our Hypertext 2014 paper (jointly presented with &lt;a href="http://www.dcs.gla.ac.uk/~mounia/"&gt;Mounia Lalmas&lt;/a&gt;) titled: &lt;a href="http://scholar.google.es/citations?view_op=view_citation&amp;amp;hl=es&amp;amp;user=ltsTTI4AAAAJ&amp;amp;citation_for_view=ltsTTI4AAAAJ:Tiz5es2fbqcC"&gt;Balancing Diversity to Counter-measure Geographical Centralization in Microblogging Platforms&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have evaluated our algorithm in user studies and the results have been great. In addition, we are working on visualizations of the timelines generated by our algorithm, so expect more cool things to come, specially in &lt;em&gt;news&lt;/em&gt; contexts. We want to make user interfaces that show news about the &lt;em&gt;whole&lt;/em&gt; country, not just about Santiago :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this project, besides my advisors &lt;a href="http://baeza.cl/"&gt;Ricardo Baeza-Yates&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.dcs.gla.ac.uk/~mounia/"&gt;Mounia Lalmas&lt;/a&gt;, I have been lucky to collaborate with &lt;a href="http://www.barbara.cl"&gt;Bárbara Poblete&lt;/a&gt; and to receive feedback and advice from &lt;a href="http://researchswinger.org/"&gt;Daniele Quercia&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://upf.academia.edu/DiegoSaezTrumper"&gt;Diego Sáez-Trumper&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bonus:&lt;/strong&gt; researching people and its behavior has allowed us to find interesting things which are not directly related to our main research question. For instance, consider the following image that shows user registrations on Chile (see the right figure):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/web-mining-2014-chilean-users.png" width="600" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notice the &lt;em&gt;peak&lt;/em&gt;? It's the week of the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2010_Chile_earthquake"&gt;27F Earthquake from 2010&lt;/a&gt;, one of the largest earthquakes ever. I remember how Twitter was used to spread information and help others (unfortunately, other people misused it as well). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Resources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1307.0219"&gt;Ornitología Virtual&lt;/a&gt; (paper in spanish to be published in the up-coming book &lt;em&gt;Socializar Conocimientos II: Observando a Chile desde la Distancia&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1309.1785"&gt;#Santiago is not #Chile, or is it? A Model to Normalize Social Media Impact&lt;/a&gt; Presented at the 1st Chilean Conference on Human Computer Interaction.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://scholar.google.es/citations?view_op=view_citation&amp;amp;hl=es&amp;amp;user=ltsTTI4AAAAJ&amp;amp;citation_for_view=ltsTTI4AAAAJ:Tiz5es2fbqcC"&gt;Balancing Diversity to Counter-measure Geographical Centralization in Microblogging Platforms&lt;/a&gt;, to be presented at the Hypertext 2014 conference in Santiago, Chile.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><category term="visualization"></category><category term="social network analysis"></category><category term="web mining"></category><category term="twitter"></category><category term="chile"></category></entry><entry><title>2013 Italian Elections in Yahoo News</title><link href="http://carnby.github.io/2013-italian-elections-in-yahoo-news.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-01-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>egraells</name></author><id>tag:carnby.github.io,2013-01-01:2013-italian-elections-in-yahoo-news.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In 2013, within the &lt;em&gt;Social Media Engagement Research Group&lt;/em&gt; in &lt;a href="http://labs.yahoo.com/location/barcelona/"&gt;Yahoo Labs Barcelona&lt;/a&gt; (group led by &lt;a href="http://alexjaimes.com/"&gt;Alejandro Jaimes&lt;/a&gt;) we developed two visualizations to analyze and explore the presidential elections in Italy. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Social Media Support&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/visualizations-2013-italian-elections-map.jpg" width="600" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each  map is colored according to the &lt;em&gt;social media support index&lt;/em&gt; of each party. This index was estimated from the amount of Facebook likes and Twitter retweets supporting the different political parties. You can see that different regions had different support levels. In the overview map, each region is colored according to the &lt;em&gt;most&lt;/em&gt; supported party, but you can see the whole party support by clicking on the top buttons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Visualization featured in Yahoo News&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/visualizations-2013-italian-elections-metrics.png" width="600" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We performed data mining on Twitter to analyze how each candidate's tweets were related to several issues like education, health care, and so on. Then, we compared how each candidate gave importance to each issue in comparison to the other candidates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Bonus Track: Playing with color scales in maps&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/visualizations-2013-italian-elections-minimaps.png" width="600" /&gt;
&lt;img src="images/visualizations-2013-italian-elections-minimaps-scales.png" width="600" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this project I started to like maps a lot, specially in &lt;em&gt;small multiples contexts&lt;/em&gt;. Although the menu in the map visualization uses colored buttons, originally we wanted to have these small multiples. But sometimes cross-browser technology (remember that a big share of Web surfers still use Internet Explorer) won't allow you to do what you want.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="visualization"></category><category term="elections"></category><category term="italy"></category><category term="news"></category></entry><entry><title>Sentiment Visualization Widgets</title><link href="http://carnby.github.io/sentiment-visualization-widgets.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-01-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>egraells</name></author><id>tag:carnby.github.io,2013-01-01:sentiment-visualization-widgets.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;After working on search engines previously, and the experience of Timebook, we started to explore the design space of visualizations in the context of exploration of historical figures. In particular, we focused on how history has judged historical figures, through the usage of sentiment analysis over Wikipedia biographies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Visualizing Sentiment through History&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/visualizations-2013-sentiment-history.png" width="600" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Visualizing Negative and Positive Ontologies in DBPedia&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/visualizations-2013-sentiment-treemap.png" width="600" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Which widget is better to foster visual exploration?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/visualizations-2013-sentiment-search.png" width="600" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/visualizations-2013-sentiment-search-2.png" width="600" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results of these experiments will be presented (jointly with my advisors &lt;a href="http://baeza.cl/"&gt;Ricardo Baeza-Yates&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.dcs.gla.ac.uk/~mounia/"&gt;Mounia Lalmas&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href="http://columbus.exp.sis.pitt.edu/sp2014/"&gt;1st Social Personalization Workshop&lt;/a&gt; to be held at the &lt;a href="http://ht.acm.org/ht2014"&gt;Hypertext 2014&lt;/a&gt; conference in Santiago, Chile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Resources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://ceur-ws.org/Vol-1210/SP2014_03.pdf"&gt;Sentiment Visualisation Widgets for Exploratory Search&lt;/a&gt; paper at the &lt;a href="http://ceur-ws.org/Vol-1210/"&gt;Hypertext 2014 Extended Proceedings&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><category term="visualization"></category><category term="time-series"></category><category term="sentiment analysis"></category><category term="exploration"></category><category term="dbpedia"></category></entry><entry><title>Faceted Exploration</title><link href="http://carnby.github.io/faceted-exploration.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-01-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>egraells</name></author><id>tag:carnby.github.io,2012-01-01:faceted-exploration.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/visualizations-2012-identified.png" width="600" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the summer of 2012 (in the northern hemisphere), we moved (my wife and me) from Barcelona to San Francisco to do an internship at Identified. Identified was a startup about gamification of job-seeking social networks, plus candidate sourcing for recruiters (it was acquired by Workday). I fully designed and implemented a search engine that used visualization widgets plus faceted search and filtering.
My mentor through the internship was &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/steelbot"&gt;James Fan&lt;/a&gt;. Thanks for all your guidance, James!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="search"></category><category term="exploration"></category><category term="internship"></category></entry><entry><title>Gender Equality Index</title><link href="http://carnby.github.io/gender-equality-index.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-01-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>egraells</name></author><id>tag:carnby.github.io,2012-01-01:gender-equality-index.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/visualizations-2012-gender-equality.png" width="600" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Motivated by the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Women%27s_Day"&gt;International Working Women's Day&lt;/a&gt;, I wanted to explore the &lt;a href="http://www.socialwatch.org/node/14367"&gt;Gender Equity Index dataset released by SocialWatch&lt;/a&gt; with their indicators of Gender Quality Index. In particular I wanted to find out how is my own country, Chile, in terms of equality in comparison with other countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a experiment to learn how to work with maps in &lt;code&gt;d3.js&lt;/code&gt;. See the visualization &lt;a href="http://dcc.uchile.cl/~egraells/gender_equality/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone should have the same access to the same opportunities. Hopefully, one day these maps will have only one color.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="gender"></category><category term="equality"></category><category term="visualization"></category><category term="maps"></category></entry><entry><title>Linspiration</title><link href="http://carnby.github.io/linspiration.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-01-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>egraells</name></author><id>tag:carnby.github.io,2012-01-01:linspiration.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/visualizations-2012-linspiration.png" width="600" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Linspiration&lt;/em&gt; is a visualization technique implemented in &lt;code&gt;d3.js&lt;/code&gt; to explore and compare time-series in a fun way. This was one of the first explorations in my PhD into designing &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; visualizations. It all started in the brainstorming sessions with &lt;a href="http://alexjaimes.com/"&gt;Alejandro Jaimes&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://grupoweb.upf.edu/~luca.chiarandini/"&gt;Luca Chiarandini&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://panchotolchinsky.com/"&gt;Pancho Tolchinsky&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://meekalbajaj.com/"&gt;Meekal Bajaj&lt;/a&gt;. I have learned so much from them!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Presented jointly with &lt;a href="http://alexjaimes.com/"&gt;Alejandro Jaimes&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href="http://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2166966&amp;amp;picked=prox"&gt;2012 Intelligent User Interfaces&lt;/a&gt; conference in Lisbon, Portugal.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="visualization"></category><category term="time-series"></category><category term="fun"></category><category term="exploration"></category></entry><entry><title>EU Hackathons</title><link href="http://carnby.github.io/eu-hackathons.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-01-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>egraells</name></author><id>tag:carnby.github.io,2011-01-01:eu-hackathons.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have participated in all editions of the &lt;a href="http://euhackathon.eu"&gt;EU Hackathon&lt;/a&gt;, a series of events organized by the European Parliament and Google in Brussels. In the last two editions, I teamed up with my two great friends &lt;a href="http://grupoweb.upf.edu/~luca.chiarandini/"&gt;Luca Chiarandini&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://upf.academia.edu/DiegoSaezTrumper"&gt;Diego Sáez-Trumper&lt;/a&gt;. We were "Team Bodoques".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;2013 Edition (Data Sovereignty Project)&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/visualizations-2013-data-sovereignity.png" width="600" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We developed a metric named &lt;em&gt;data sovereigny&lt;/em&gt; as the quality of having independent authority over citizens' information. In the &lt;a href="http://www.visualizing.org/visualizations/data-sovereignty"&gt;visualization&lt;/a&gt; we can observe how user data flows across important and popular websites, which are geolocated to the countries their servers lie in. We highlight those sites that track users through a &lt;em&gt;tracking score&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;2012 Edition (Eye Time Project)&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;iframe src="http://prezi.com/embed/ezhjfp7nidez/?bgcolor=ffffff&amp;amp;lock_to_path=0&amp;amp;autoplay=0&amp;amp;autohide_ctrls=0&amp;amp;features=undefined&amp;amp;disabled_features=undefined&amp;amp;html5=1" width="600" height="400" frameBorder="0" webkitAllowFullScreen mozAllowFullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our project was a Chrome browser extension (plus server side logic and processing) that allowed children to monitor their Web usage. In particular, Web usage of learning websites allowed children to spend more time online. Parents were able to understand the Web browsing habits of their kids. We &lt;a href="http://2012.euhackathon.eu/team-bodoques-3-spainitaly-filtering-analytics-of-children-behaviours/"&gt;won the &lt;em&gt;Children Safety Track&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;2011 Edition (Ananke Project)&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/visualizations-2011-ananke.png" width="600" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Solo participation&lt;/em&gt;. In this edition, I explored the differences in geographical distribution of variables related to internet quality in Europe, along features extracted from The World Bank. Here is feedback written about the visualization (&lt;a href="http://citizenlab.org/2011/11/citizen-lab-at-the-eu-hackathon/"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;Eduardo has an obvious awareness of data visualization fundamentals and best practices, and for the hackathon he developed a working prototype as well as two mockups of interactive visualizations meant to support data exploration and decision making. Like Team Ferioli’s entry the prototype incorporates economic indicators, displaying World Bank statistics alongside M-Lab data. The difference (aside from data source) is how comparisons are made. Instead of placing a bubble over each country on a single map, two map views are displayed in parallel, a user-selectable variable displayed on each. The different approaches have different strengths. The single map with bubbles makes discrepancies such as those described above stand out and be found more quickly, and doesn't require moving your eyes back and forth between maps. On the other hand, I find it easier to spot geographic trends within individual variables with Eduardo's approach, without the bubbles disrupting the visual flow. Also, props to Eduardo for choosing a colorblind-friendly colour palette. I don't know whether it was a conscious decision but it is an important consideration, often overlooked by visualization developers.&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><category term="hackathon"></category><category term="europe"></category><category term="maps"></category><category term="children"></category><category term="privacy"></category></entry><entry><title>Timebook</title><link href="http://carnby.github.io/timebook.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-01-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>egraells</name></author><id>tag:carnby.github.io,2011-01-01:timebook.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;iframe src="http://player.vimeo.com/video/50050002?color=ff9933" width="600" height="337" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/hackathon-2011-timebook.png" width=600 /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Timebook&lt;/em&gt; is a social network of historical figures built from Linked Open Data found on DBPedia, Europeana and WikiQuote. The main question we want to answer is: &lt;em&gt;what if social media existed before? can it be used to explore, learn and understand art movements and collections?&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joint work with &lt;a href="http://grupoweb.upf.edu/~luca.chiarandini/"&gt;Luca Chiarandini&lt;/a&gt;. Code available at &lt;a href="https://github.com/carnby/timebook"&gt;github&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Winners of the Social Inclusion category and Developers Award&lt;/strong&gt; at &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://pro.europeana.eu/hack4europe-spain-11"&gt;Europeana's Hack4Europe hackathon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; in Barcelona. We also thank &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/innova2"&gt;Conxa Rodà&lt;/a&gt; for her support and encouragement to present our work at the &lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/relaxintheair/7262241786/"&gt;Museum Next&lt;/a&gt; conference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Covered here:
 *
 * &lt;a href="http://www.blogmuseupicassobcn.org/2011/06/what-do-the-museu-picasso-europeana-and-cultural-hackers-have-in-common/?lang=en"&gt;blog post at Museu Picasso&lt;/a&gt;
 * &lt;a href="http://tecnologia.elpais.com/tecnologia/2011/06/09/actualidad/1307610066_850215.html"&gt;Coverage at "El País" (in spanish)&lt;/a&gt;
 * &lt;a href="http://europa.eu/rapid/press-release_IP-11-723_en.htm?locale=FR"&gt;Press release at Europa.eu&lt;/a&gt;
 * &lt;a href="http://www.blogmuseupicassobcn.org/2011/06/after-the-digital-agenda-assembly-in-brussels/?lang=en"&gt;blog post about presentation of Timebook at European Digital Assembly Agenda&lt;/a&gt;
 * &lt;a href="http://prezi.com/z6lxt3uf9l5y/timebook-museumnext-2012/?utm_source=prezi-view&amp;amp;utm_medium=ending-screen&amp;amp;utm_campaign=ending-screen&amp;amp;utm_content=Title_link"&gt;presentation at Museum Next&lt;/a&gt;
 * &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GSyNSMmFBSI"&gt;interview on Linked Open Data at the Citilab Europeana Workshop&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="hackathon"></category><category term="social networks"></category><category term="dbpedia"></category><category term="art"></category><category term="museums"></category></entry><entry><title>UN Global Voices</title><link href="http://carnby.github.io/un-global-voices.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-01-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>egraells</name></author><id>tag:carnby.github.io,2011-01-01:un-global-voices.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/visualizations-2011-global-voices.png" width="600" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I participated on a visualization contest about United Nations data from the Voices of the Vulnerable program. The visualization tries to resume more than 500 answers in natural language to questions about how the people feel about their current economic situations and their future. Our work did not win but it received &lt;a href="http://www.unglobalpulse.org/blog/%E2%80%9Cvisualize-voices-vulnerable%E2%80%9D-design-challenge-winners"&gt;good feedback&lt;/a&gt;. Joint work with &lt;a href="http://www.ruthygarcia.com/"&gt;Ruth Garcia Gavilanes&lt;/a&gt; from Yahoo/UPF.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;The Visualization submitted by Eduardo Graells Garrido raises the critical question of the complexity of classifying natural language with grammar errors and ambiguity. It shows a very interesting graph representation that classifies the topics related to changes in the last year (Q3).&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See the visualization &lt;a href="http://dcc.uchile.cl/~egraells/un_visualization/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. It has been features on the &lt;a href="http://blogs.lse.ac.uk/impactofsocialsciences/2013/10/02/social-media-data-public-policy-leavey/"&gt;Impact Blog of the London School of Economics and Political Science&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="united nations"></category><category term="global voices"></category><category term="visualization"></category></entry><entry><title>Visualization of #20N</title><link href="http://carnby.github.io/visualization-of-20n.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-01-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>egraells</name></author><id>tag:carnby.github.io,2011-01-01:visualization-of-20n.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/visualizations-2011-20n-spain.png" width="600" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the first projects I did on the PhD. I implemented a real-time visualization that displayed how Twitter reacted to the on-going presidential elections in Spain in November 20th, 2011. It was one of my first experiments with &lt;code&gt;django + d3.js&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="elections"></category><category term="twitter"></category><category term="visualization"></category></entry><entry><title>Transantiago - Corridor Speeds</title><link href="http://carnby.github.io/transantiago-corridor-speeds.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-01-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>egraells</name></author><id>tag:carnby.github.io,2010-01-01:transantiago-corridor-speeds.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/transantiago-2010-speeds.png" width="600" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I worked in the Department of Civil Engineering, Transport Division at University of Chile, under the supervision of &lt;a href="http://www.cec.uchile.cl/~dicidet/marcela.html"&gt;Marcela Munizaga&lt;/a&gt;. My main task was to develop tools to analyze corridor speeds in the &lt;em&gt;Transantiago&lt;/em&gt; public transport system. Corridor speeds were estimated according to GPS information from all vehicles on the system.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="maps"></category><category term="public transport"></category><category term="transantiago"></category></entry><entry><title>Non Photorealistic Rendering (Master Thesis)</title><link href="http://carnby.github.io/non-photorealistic-rendering-master-thesis.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2009-01-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>egraells</name></author><id>tag:carnby.github.io,2009-01-01:non-photorealistic-rendering-master-thesis.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My Master's thesis was about a non photorealistic rendering technique called &lt;em&gt;hatching&lt;/em&gt;. Hatching imitates hand-drawn lines to shade objects. In the thesis, I developed an algorithm to hatch animated objects, as previous approaches focus on static ones. 
The implementation is made on C++. It is based on the &lt;a href="http://gfx.cs.princeton.edu/proj/lapped_tex/"&gt;Real Time Hatching&lt;/a&gt; algorithm, which in turn uses the &lt;a href="http://gfx.cs.princeton.edu/proj/lapped_tex/"&gt;Lapped Textures&lt;/a&gt; algorithm.
My advisor was &lt;a href="http://users.dcc.uchile.cl/~mcrivara/indexen.html"&gt;María Cecilia Rivara&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/master-thesis-2008-donut.png" width="600" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/master-thesis-2008-anim-1.png" width="600" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/master-thesis-2008-tool-1.png" width="600" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/master-thesis-2008-tool-2.png" width="600" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/master-thesis-2008-atst.jpg" width="600" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/master-thesis-2008-samus.jpg" width="600" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Resources: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.tesis.uchile.cl/tesis/uchile/2010/cf-graells_eg/html/index.html"&gt;Thesis&lt;/a&gt; (in spanish). &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/carnby/Zahir"&gt;Zahir framework at github&lt;/a&gt;, including the implementation of Lapped Textures.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><category term="computer graphics"></category><category term="rendering"></category><category term="art"></category><category term="c++"></category></entry><entry><title>Chileclic - Search Engine for the Chilean Government</title><link href="http://carnby.github.io/chileclic-search-engine-for-the-chilean-government.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2008-01-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>egraells</name></author><id>tag:carnby.github.io,2008-01-01:chileclic-search-engine-for-the-chilean-government.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/ciw-2009-chileclic.png" width="600" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chileclic was a search engine from the government developed at &lt;a href="http://www.ciw.cl"&gt;Center for Web Research &lt;/a&gt;. I designed and implemented the search user interface, which needed to be embedded into the original design of the site. The development included a back-end dashboard of query analytics.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="search"></category><category term="government"></category></entry><entry><title>Zahir: Rendering Framework</title><link href="http://carnby.github.io/zahir-rendering-framework.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2007-01-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>egraells</name></author><id>tag:carnby.github.io,2007-01-01:zahir-rendering-framework.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;To become an &lt;em&gt;engineer in computer science&lt;/em&gt; I designed and developed a framework for computer graphics, focused on implementation of shading algorithms, in particular non photorealistic techniques.
The framework is called &lt;em&gt;Zahir&lt;/em&gt; and it was implemented in C++. My advisor was &lt;a href="http://users.dcc.uchile.cl/~mcrivara/indexen.html"&gt;María Cecilia Rivara&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/memoria-2007-shading-marvin.png" width="600" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/memoria-2007-shading-utah.png" width="600" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/memoria-2007-shading-rabbit.png" width="600" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="images/memoria-2007-shading-tiger.png" width="600" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Resources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.tesis.uchile.cl/tesis/uchile/2008/graells_eg/sources/graells_eg.pdf"&gt;Engineering Thesis&lt;/a&gt; (in spanish)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1309.1917"&gt;Zahir: a Object-Oriented Framework for Computer Graphics&lt;/a&gt; Technical Report that summarizes the thesis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><category term="computer graphics"></category><category term="framework"></category><category term="rendering"></category><category term="engineering"></category><category term="c++"></category></entry></feed>